[Music]
hello greetings people of earth i come
in peace hello
uh welcome to uh the ask a video show
today we are talking about science
a very nice non-controversial topic
no geopolitics no history just science
so let's see who all is here with us i
can see zainab samarth tejas siddharth
[Music]
and a whole lot of people
great to see you all great to see you
all so let us go into the questions i
have as always picked up a bunch of
questions that you've asked
and i will endeavor
to answer as many of them as possible
so let us begin with the questions
and let's begin with this one
so swatnil says is terra forming the
sahara desert or australia possible
for making a place habitable or would it
disrupt weather and climatic patterns
around the world
terra forming the sahara desert or
australia
see the earth is a single system
the atmosphere the the land the oceans
it's all tied together
in a well it's all it's all uh
everything is interrelated so if you
change one aspect of any of these things
everything else will uh
kind of react to that
so if you
say you want to uh make the sahara
desert lush green again it's possible it
can be done with with
engineering projects and all you dig you
create canals that bring in water from
somewhere else possibly
uh
or or some other means of doing it so
yeah you could possibly do it over a
period of time maybe 50 years or so
because these
projects would take time
so it would certainly make the place
more habitable you could do it in the
australian outback australia is a very
dry added place most of it the entire
continent it's possible to do that
it would certainly change the weather
and climate patterns around the world
because it's all uninterrelated
uh
so certainly it's possible but it would
definitely change things around now in
the past
we know that the sahara desert was lush
green well maybe a hundred thousand or
so years ago or maybe before that there
have been these uh
cyclical patterns in the history of the
earth in which
there are
times when there are this cold cold
weather the ice age and all that there
are times of
dry climate in the sahara like we see
now and there are times when there is
much more rainfall and
places are more
lush green so it's been there but if you
change this you will certainly see the
entire world's weather change
and the patterns
change the monsoon may change in india
depending on various factors so it would
certainly change it would not disrupt
weather and climate it would change
weather and climate if you make such uh
large scale changes
in the
geography of the earth right
okay the next question is about climate
change climate change is a very uh
important thing so
for 30 to 40 years down the line what
are the major changes that are going to
happen to the earth's climate what will
be the consequences
and something geopolitical game going on
see climate change is a thing there's no
doubt about it it's always been around
climate change is something that you
cannot really
question it's there
so what's going to happen in the next 30
40 years we know that the amount of
carbon particulate matter in the
atmosphere is increasing it's it
may be an all-time high or something i
don't have the statistics you can look
it up
um
so what that does is that it intensifies
the global warming it causes this
greenhouse greenhouse effect
and
it's making our climate warmer i believe
in the next hundred or so years we are
projected to have
a rise an increase in the average global
temperature by maybe two percent or so
which is significant two percent may
look a little very small but uh in the
global context it's quite uh quite high
it will cause
uh
a lot of ice
to melt in the polar regions more mostly
antarctica
the arctic region
uh in the north near the north pole
and you already witnessing this you're
seeing this happen
now climate change has always been a
thing
it's always been around for millions of
years hundreds of millions of years
uh if you look at the entire geological
history of the planet it's been
a constant story of climate change even
in india
seven eight thousand years ago the
indian
monsoon was much more intense there used
to be much more rainfall about eight
thousand years ago
and then about eight or so thousand
years ago six thousand bc
onwards
the uh monsoon started declining
monotonically and today we receive far
less rainfall than we used to receive 8
000 years ago and that caused a lot of
changes in india the an entire river
disappeared right
and so on so these things have always
been part of our history but right now
there is a significant
man-made component to the climate change
and because of that we are witnessing
global warming so in 30 40 50 years
we're going to have an increase in the
global temperatures or average
temperature so let's say you are in a
place where the average temperature
today is 25 degrees throughout the year
if you average the temperatures
throughout the year you get an average
of 25 degrees maybe in 40 50 years it
may be 26 degrees
right
that sort of thing
so you're gonna have these changes the
ocean levels will rise as the ice melts
in the in the polar regions
and
in fifty hundred fifty or years or a
hundred years many of the low-lying
areas the coastal regions in various
parts of the world could kind of go
underwater
uh you may have an increase in the
average uh
water levels
sea levels worldwide maybe by
i don't know how much it's exactly going
to be a foot two feet that's that's a
lot actually
so many low-lying island nations could
disappear there are some islands island
nations in the south pacific region
small island nations that could be in
trouble the maldives could disappear
bangladesh
could have a lot of trouble and people
are saying that india should
absorb
the bangladesh operation that will be
affected by this so
all of these things are going to happen
they're gonna see this even in india in
various coastal cities
kolkata mumbai
chennai etc you could see some
consequences of this rise in the sea
level
so if you're planning to buy property
somewhere in one of these metropolitan
cities you may want to buy it on higher
ground
uh
at some distance from the sea coast
perhaps
so that's that's the kind of thing we're
gonna witness it's gonna happen it's
happening it's it's a process that's
already in motion uh with the
geopolitical game going on is it
stoppable you can't stop it
it's what we can do is we can try and
prevent further
change we can try and slow down the the
pace of change we can try and ensure
that we don't dump more
pollution more carbon into the
atmosphere we can try and reduce the
carbon output the carbon footprint of
every country and so on that's what we
can do but what's already going on
cannot be stopped it's going to happen
it's going to happen anyway
uh
so it's it's almost impossible to stop
this because every nation is competing
with each other there are countries that
have been destroyed over the past 500
years 500 years by colonialism they want
to rise again and the only way to rise
again is through industrialization
industrialization has a carbon footprint
what can you do about it you can't ask
the countries the west cannot ask the
countries it has destroyed in the past
500 years to stop developing
it just won't work so it's just a
natural consequence of
development and development is required
we have such a huge population so
there's a whole range of factors in this
but it's going to happen
it's happening
okay they just asks is it possible that
jupiter has eaten up
other planets as some latest study
suggests
right so what is jupiter uh
i hope you all know the solar system
what it's like can you name the planets
can you name the planets starting from
the sun onwards so let me tell you if we
have the sun
then we have mercury venus then the
earth then you have mars then you have
the asteroid belt
then you have jupiter saturn uranus
neptune pluto then you have further uh
uh there's a whole bunch of planets
called the trans uh uh not planets even
pluto is no longer classified as a
planet and so on then you have the
uh objects that are beyond pluto the
minor planets the planetary symbols you
have the old clown comments comets much
more the trojan asteroids various other
asteroids and so on so we're talking
about jupiter
so jupiter is uh the largest planet in
the solar system it's also believed to
be the it it is also most likely the
oldest planet in the solar system it's
the first large first overall planet
that formed out of the proto
uh st
excuse me proto stellar uh uh gas cloud
right from the primordial solar system
um so uh the solar system's age is about
4.57 billion years yeah and jupiter is
believed to have formed the solid core
of jupiter is believed to have formed
about between one million years and five
million years after the start of the
solar system's history so it's the
oldest planet that we know of
earth so so jupiter is about four and a
half billion years old
the earth is also about that old but
slightly younger than that
and as we know jupiter is about 320
times the mass of the earth it is one
thousandth the mass of the sun so that's
about jupiter so is it possible that
jupiter has eaten up other planets it is
entirely possible see the old the early
solar system was a very dynamic place
there was a lot of chaos
it's possible there were certain planets
called super earths that were formed in
the possibly in the inner solar system
inner solar system means between the
orbit of
uh
between the sun and the orbit of
present-day orbit of jupiter it's
present that certain very large rocky
planets
were formed in the early solar system
uh
in this period right and because of the
very dynamic nature of the solar system
at that time there would have been
collisions between these super
earth-like planets which possibly uh
gave rise to the asteroid belt that we
witnessed between the orbits of mars
mass and jupiter it's also possible that
jupiter was earlier formed when it was
formed it was at a different location
at a different distance away from the
solar from the sun maybe
much further
outwards
and then because of the
gravitational dynamics it came inwards
and it shepherded certain planets and it
gave rise to the order that we see today
so it is certainly almost
almost 99.9 probably it has eaten up
swallowed up
ancient planets in the past and
certainly lots of debris rocky debris
etc it has definitely done that we have
witnessed uh
about 20 or so years ago
maybe before that the uh
the crash
of the of the comet shoemaker levy into
jupiter
the or the gravity of the planet first
store the shredded the comet into
multiple pieces and then those pieces
eventually ended up hitting
the planet jupiter and this was
witnessed
we can you can see photographs of that
available online
and so it swallowed up that comet in the
past there would have been lots of
events like that even entire planets
would have
possibly been swallowed by jupiter so i
don't know which study you're referring
to but it is definitely very likely that
this happened even saturn would have
swallowed up certain planets it's also
quite likely that earth itself
in its uh early phase was hit by we know
that there was a massive bombardment the
so-called hedian period
but it's quite likely that the earth
itself was hit by
a large planet in the very ancient past
maybe about about four and a half four
point three four point four billion
years before today and that collision
most likely possibly gave rise to the
moon right so yeah it's a very
interesting history we don't know a lot
about it but depending on what we see
today we can kind of reconstruct the
earlier older history of the solar
system so yes it is quite possible that
jupiter has eaten up like you say
other planets in the past
okay
says will humanity ever get success in
finding alien life at all
do aliens exist
if they do can we ever reach them or get
a glimpse of them are we really alone in
the universe
see
it's possible
that we may discover alien life next
weekend next week it's possible it's
also possible that we may never ever
find aliens
any trace of alien life
both possibilities are i would say
equally likely do i believe aliens exist
i am pretty sure they that aliens exist
i'm pretty sure that life exists in
other places possibly in our own solar
system there could be life in the
microbial form or something
maybe on on mars perhaps buried under
the soil
maybe on europa maybe on titan
maybe somewhere else it's quite possible
so
microbial life could exist right now in
our solar system
uh beyond the earth
when we talk about intelligent life if
you just see the sheer number of
stars galaxies planets that you have
it's it's almost impossible to imagine
that with 10 rays of 23 or 24 stars in
the visible universe
i mean is it i mean if if we are the
only
place where life exists that doesn't
make any sense so i am personally quite
sure that life exists in other places
maybe even intelligent life most likely
there will be other
civilizations that could be just as
intelligent or more
intelligent more advanced more evolved
than us but for some reason we are not
able to
detect them we have never been able to
detect them in recorded history from
whatever we know there is no unambiguous
evidence that we have found aliens in
the past some people say that there are
certain
carvings on pyramids or rocks or
whatever that seem to depict alien
visitations well it's not unambiguous
evidence it seems to look like uh
something that resembles a spacecraft or
somebody or a human or a figure of a
human being or something that seems to
wear a kind of helmet that you would
imagine in science fiction movies but
that is not unambiguous evidence
so uh
so the question is why are we not able
to detect alien life if it is if it
should be so uh
widespread and common in the universe
well
maybe we are not evolved enough
maybe we are too primitive we may think
that we all think that we are so
advanced in all in the modern world we
have all this technology and all that
but
most likely we are still a very
primitive species right
think about it this way
let's say you have a petri dish
in which you have a colony of bacteria
okay it's in a lab it's sitting in a lab
scientists are studying this colony of
bacteria a few million bacteria in a
petri dish a dish which is sealed
and the
the colony of bacteria is let's say 300
generations old so bacteria they divide
they reproduce
they die off and the descendants again
do the same thing it goes on and on and
let's say this colony of bacteria is
let's say a thousand generations old
yeah
so these bacteria they're sitting in
there
and they're talking to each other each
other
they're wondering do other life forms
exist
yeah
they're having this discussion among
each other these bacteria that we have
been living here for a thousand
generations at least our history is very
ancient
and we have never found evidence of
alien life
they're talking to each other
and just outside what they can perceive
there are scientists human scientists
who are studying them through the
microscope so the bacteria don't have
the sensory apparatus
that is needed to see the scientists the
bacteria are so small the scientists are
so far away
relatively compared to them
so even though the scientists are
observing the bacteria the bacteria have
no idea that they are being observed so
maybe we are also
in a way
those bacteria
and maybe there's somebody observing us
when we are simply not aware of it we
know that 95 percent of the universe is
unknown to us it's dark
dark matter dark energy we don't have
the least idea of what these things are
so maybe there's something going on out
there that we're not aware of and they
know we are here and they may be
studying us
for a few thousand generations and we
just simply not aware of it yeah the
time scales that we live in 100 years 70
years it must be just a fraction of a
second to maybe to this hypothetical
alien species so that is entirely
possible so maybe it's all out there but
we simply not able to see it because we
are too primitive and our senses are too
limited entirely possible so
so i don't have definitive answers are
we alone in the universe i don't know i
don't think so i don't think so can we
ever reach them get a glimpse of them
who knows
so let's see how it goes hopefully we
will find something
and hopefully that will not be too
dangerous yeah right
okay dark lord the dark lord is here all
right is time travel really possible can
you explain the grandfather paradox and
just by
says according what according to
theoretical physicists are the possible
ways to travel back in time other than
wormhole concept in which there's a
requirement of cosmic strings and
negative mass and negative energy
theoretically of course can you please
share some of the hypothesis about
traveling back in time is there any
solution to paradoxes such as the
grandfather paradox the bootstrap
paradox etc
what is the grandfather paradox uh
imagine a scenario a hypothetical
scenario in which you
can go back in time let's say you go
back in time 80 years
and then you you discover a person you
you meet various people back in time 80
years back in time and you
meet a person
you get into some kind of argument with
the person you end up killing the person
yeah
and just by chance by by by terrible
chance that person happens to be your
grandfather
yeah
so you go back in time you for whatever
reason end up killing your own
grandfather
then how is it that you exist
that causes
that that breaks causality
there is a causal chain in the world i
always keep talking about the causal
chain the cause effect uh
relationship
everything that exists today exists
because of things that happen in the
past the causal change cause and effect
cause and effect goes back millions
billions billions of years it goes back
13.7 billion years the cause and effect
chain
which is the the timeline of the big
bang right
so if you go back in time if crime if
time travel were possible if it were
possible to go back in time you go back
in time you kill your own grandfather
then how the hell do you exist
it makes no sense and yet there it is so
that kind of tells you that there is a
there is that the causal structure of
the universe breaks down if try time
travel happens right
then there is something called like
jaspreet says the bootstrap paradox
that's another paradox let's say
i'm sitting here
now i have been studying physics my
entire life i know relativity the
special theory of relativity the general
theory of relativity now who came up
with relativity it was albert einstein
he published the special theory in 1905
and the general theory of relativity in
1915. i know these theories because i've
studied them right
i know the equations i have actually
done the work not just reading uh
popular science books and magazines so
let's say i travel back in time yeah
i travel back in time i go back to
1904 one year before einstein published
these theories at the first theory
so i go back in time a year before or
let's say five years before einstein
published relativity
i meet einstein
and i teach him relativity
i teach him the entire math all the
equations everything i give him the
entire
theory
that he eventually ends up publishing
and then he goes ahead and publishes it
because he learned it from me
but i learned it from him
but he learned it from me
so who
came up with the theory first i go back
in time and teach it to him but i learnt
it from him with himself
so who's the originator of the theory
once again the causal structure of the
universe gets messed up
so that is the bootstrap paradox there
are multiple versions of this you can
imagine all kinds of scenarios in which
this thing gets messed up the bootstrap
paradox and all that
uh right so that's that's what it is so
the question then is uh is time travel
really possible that's a real question
so general relativity permits some exact
solutions that allow for time travel and
some of these exact solutions they
describe what is known as they describe
universes that contain what's known as
closed time-like curves these are world
lines that lead back to the same point
in space time not only in time in space
but in time in time as well so these are
called closed time-like curves so at a
closed time like curve it's a world line
of a material particle in space time so
this word line is closed it it keeps it
returns to its starting point so if a
particle or or a person let's say is
inside that
you go back
it's like a loop you can't you can
travel back in time so in this you can
travel backwards in time
but not forwards
so that's called a causal loop and uh
even when it comes to wormholes
a wormhole what's a wormhole a wormhole
is like well it looks like a black hole
from the outside but it's it's a tunnel
with two mouths and a throat that
connects the two mouths
so
let's say you have a wormhole which is
which is open for whatever it is and
first of all wormhole solutions are very
uh
wormholes want to snapshot snapshot it's
almost impossible to keep it open unless
you have something called exotic
material like something with the
negative mass
we have never seen any material that has
negative mass right but let's say such a
thing it's hypothetically theoretically
possible
so if you have something like that you
can keep the wormhole open or if you
have something called a cosmic string
which is a defect in the structure of
space-time
hypothetical again if you have these
things you could keep a wormhole open
and you could that could then become a
traversable wormhole so let's say you
have a wormhole with one mouth in one
place the other mouth far away in
spacetime and the other mouth is
traveling at relativistic velocities so
if you go from one point from one
opening and you end up with the other
you may end up going backwards in time
so these are
possible scenarios in which you could
actually travel backwards in time
so
that's what i can offer you so these are
uh
possible ways in which hypothetically
theoretically you could possibly go back
in time but the question is does it
violate causality it could possibly be a
violent causality that we just spoke of
the grandfather paradox the bootstrap
paradox and so on if it were possible
secondly it could even violate the
second law of thermodynamics entropy
what does the second law of
thermodynamics say
well one of the ways of putting it is
that systems always flow from a state of
order to a state of disorder entropy
always increases
so an object that's trapped within a a
time loop
or any information that is dropped
within a time loop would continue to age
and eventually disintegrate
but does it work that way so these are
the the the questions the problems that
exist and we still don't have the
actual answers
so that is where we are so there is
something about
time travel it's not entirely verboten
there are theoretical solutions that
would allow for possibly for time travel
but uh
there are but there are many unanswered
questions about causality about the
second law of thermodynamics and all
that right
so that's a little bit about it very
interesting subject very fascinating
subject and
a lot of theoretical research is going
on about this as we speak about the
causal structure of the universe does it
violate causality uh could there be an
event horizon within
within a wormhole possibly that would
kind of preclude that would kind of make
it
possible to travel without violating
causality all kinds of
uh such
research is being done and it's it's a
work in progress
okay
the question is this is a question about
what is the world's first liquid mirror
telescope developed in india
and how would it be useful for
scientific discoveries right
so i think it's being uh
it's been installed at the devastal
observatory let's take a look at that
i typically don't bring out the map
in uh
science episodes but let's do it
for a change let's bring up the map let
me open the map first and we will go and
try and find
this
observatory where's the map here's the
map
come on map
okay so let's
dive
it's in northern india it's in the
himalayas
let's see what it brings us
okay let's bring in
okay
so this is the devastal
observatory
where is it exactly located within india
as you can see it's in northern india
um
yeah that would give you the
context it's
west of the nepal india border
and south of the india tibet border
so that's where it is it's high in the
himalayas it's in a
mountainous forested region
and we have
the
ilmt the international liquid mirror
telescope
over here so that's where it is that
answers where it is now what is this
thing
right so it's not the world's first
liquid mirror telescope there have been
liquid mirror telescopes in the past
it's the largest that exists as of today
and it's not been developed in india
it's been developed by a consortium of i
think three nations india belgium canada
as far as i can recall so you can look
up the details
now what is this
so in a telescope you typically have a
lens or a mirror
in large telescopes you have reflective
mirrors and these are parabolic mirrors
typically yeah
and
so what you do is you take a big piece
of glass you you
you shape it in that in the
in the proper shape the parabolic shape
then you have to apply a
coating of some kind of reflective
material typically some sort of metal
it's a long involved process it costs a
lot of money
right so there in this devel observatory
it said there is another telescope which
cost about 20 million dollars to make
and this new telescope the liquid minute
telescope costs about one tenth of that
to make
so in a liquid mirror telescope what you
find what you have is that you have
a liquid metal typically mercury that is
set spinning and when you do that it
it it takes on the shape that's right
the the parallel the parabolic shape
that you want in a telescope
so uh
and it's it's put in a cushion of air or
something some some sort of
technological uh thing is there
and the mirror the the liquid metal the
mercury becomes it assumes that
parabolic shape and then it can be used
as a very good
mirror for a telescope
the thing about a liquid mirror
telescope is that you cannot
uh
you can't maneuver it you can't make it
point to a certain place in space in in
the sky
it just you can just place it on the
ground or wherever it is installed it
just looks upwards it looks up into a
into whatever is right above it
so that single patch in the sky
so there are pros and cons of this the
pro is that it it will focus on one
location in the sky and you can do it
night after night and add up the images
to bring out very sharp and detailed
images so that's one thing but you can't
maneuver it and make it point at some
other desired location in space
so it serves a certain purpose and it is
a it's a good technology
so it's the world's largest liquid
mineral telescope and that's what we
have right now i think it's gone
operational recently
and it's gonna be a prototype for
hopefully larger
telescopes that will be made in the
future so in a liquid mirror telescope
there are certain
restrictions you can't make it larger
than a certain
size
i think the one that we have in uh
devastating is about it has a diameter
of about four meters if i'm not mistaken
look it up
i think you try to make the telescope
bigger than let's say seven eight meters
they're gonna there's gonna be problems
because of the rotation of the earth
there is something called a coriolis
force that will distort the mirror and
then you will not get proper
images the images will be distorted
so one solution is to go to the moon
which has which is much smaller and
therefore this effect will not really
constrain us so you could make a much
larger
mirror and install it on the moon of
course the problem is how to take it
there you know
so in the future one could be able to do
that with large enough rockets like what
space x is developing and all
so it could happen in the next 20 30 40
years yeah and you could have a mirror
on the dark side of the moon let's say
that the the far side of the moon and uh
that could possibly give us very
interesting astronomical data
so that is what it is and that's what
it's used for it's used for looking at
the night sky
a certain patch of the night sky that is
right above it and it can give very nice
detailed
images
so that's about the liquid mirror
telescope in the devastating observatory
north india
the next question is by lokesh
in the context of your explanation in
the 108th session is mathematics
pseudoscience or not scientific because
it is definitive
if not what does testability and
falsifiability mean in mathematics
right so there is a question
that's a question so
is mathematics pseudoscience because
apparently there's no disability so
let's say i
i make a claim a mathematical claim i
say that 1 plus 1 is equal to 3
can it be tested let's test it
this is one
this is one pen
and i said that one plus one one equal
to three right yes another pen
what do you see i see two pens so my
hypothesis that 1 plus 1 equal to 3 has
been tested and falsified
so mathematics is
testable mathematics is definitely
falsifiable and
mathematics is all about proofs
right so we had the pythagorean theorem
the pythagorean theorem the triples uh
which you find in the bodhiana
sutras
even the babylonians were aware of it so
that is something you can test and if
you if you give a instead of saying that
a squared plus b square is equal to c
squared you said that a squared plus b
equal to c cubed you can test it that
out and you can show that that is
incorrect
it's not c cubed with c squared
you can test it out and you can even
prove or disprove theorems
using logic using the mathematical
process
entire proofs are constructed so certain
proofs take
centuries
take formats last theorem for instance
it was put forth by pierre the format in
1637 i think
in the 17th century
so it is not something that
people started believing it had to be
proven
this guy the mathematician format he
made a certain claim in one of his
notebooks or whatever
and then people are wondering whether
this claim is true or not and therefore
it had to be proven or disproven
and that process
lasted more than three centuries the the
attempt the quest for a proof of this
theorem it's only in 1995 that the
british mathematician andrew wiles was
able to finally give a definitive proof
that this theorem is correct
right and this entire process of trying
to prove this theorem led to the
development of algebraic number theory
in the 19th century in the 20th century
so you don't believe things blindly in
mathematics you have to prove it
any claim any mathematical claim that is
made
any conjecture that's made the rhyme and
conjecture or whatever it has to be
proven until it is proven it is not
nobody believes it it's something people
are trying to prove or disprove
so you have to definitely prove that
it's correct that it stands or you
definitely definitely definitely
prove mathematically that it is
incorrect
so this is pure science there is nothing
pseudo scientific about mathematics it
is 100 testable and falsifiable all
right so mathematics is
the purest of all the sciences
without mathematics there's no other
science without mathematics there is no
physics because mathematics is the
language
of physics without physics there's no
chemistry without chemistry there's no
biology and so on and so forth
so i hope that answers this question
the next question is by akash
which side are you on
will ai artificial intelligence destroy
humanity
as elon musk and a few other notable
people say or ai is extremely useful
and can speed up the advancement of
human technology beyond far beyond
anyone's imagination
you know both scenarios are possible
possible so the question is which one is
more probable see ai
is a technology
it's it's a certain
uh class of technologies
in which you have neural networks
quantum neural computing all kinds of
things which all are now classified
under the big umbrella of ai
so ai is a tool a stick is a tool
you can use it for good
purposes and for bad purposes
yeah
uh nuclear
energy is a tool
it's a technology it's a tool you can
use it to power the entire world and and
and get rid of all the polluting
technologies you can also use it to
destroy the planet with nuclear weapons
all technologies are merely tools it all
depends on how they are used you can use
them for good purposes as well as bad
purposes
you can use them for good you can use
them for harm
now ai can certainly
transform the world and and make the
world a better place
you can use uh machine learning
to
decrypt
ancient uh languages that are yet
ancient scripts that nobody has been
able to decipher thus far
you can use ai machine learning
algorithms etc to develop new drug
molecules to solve to to cure cancer and
what not
you can do all kinds of good using ai
you can use ai to monitor traffic and
and
govern the way the traffic lights change
and that can give you a better
experience in
navigating the cities for instance and
so much more
but
ai can also be used for all kinds of bad
purposes for harm
it can be used to enslave humanity
essentially using social media
algorithms using the dopamine releasing
algorithms of likes and dislikes and
shares and all that
uh
so it has all kinds of uses but
the question is who controls the ai
all the ai technologies that are
currently being developed are mostly
being being developed in certain
countries
yeah
and even in those countries let's let's
take the united states for instance and
china let's take two examples there are
more examples for sure
let's take two examples in china who's
developing the
cutting-edge ai technologies it's the
chinese government and the chinese
military that's doing it
now when the government and the military
is doing something it has
a certain purpose
a military purpose a purpose that's
about expanding your sphere of influence
at the expense of the other nations
in the u.s
the u.s military and the government are
for sure developing ai and certain very
large corporations are developing ais
ai technologies
so it's typically the government the
military and silicon valley now they
will do it for in order to benefit
themselves the large corporations will
do it
to to get even larger to to make more
money to make more to expand their
revenues and the number of people who
they influence and so on
so
if it is used for good purposes it can
transform the world but if it is used
for making money and expanding your
military influence military footprint
your geostrategic footprint it's gonna
end up causing way more trouble than we
can imagine
right
so
on balance i would the other side of
elon musk
that we need to be very very very
careful about ai
it is very useful but it can destroy the
destroy humanity it can it can possibly
end up enslaving humanity and ai doesn't
have to become conscious to destroy
humanity
ai doesn't have to be become sentient
self-aware like they show in the
terminator movies no
ai is already it can do tasks at a level
that's unimaginable for human brain
so if you automate that and if you have
human beings controlling that that gives
those human beings almost unlimited
power
and it's always for making more money
and
you could call it enslavement in the
future you could have actual enslavement
without the enslaved people realizing
they are enslaved like in the matrix
movies and so on so on balance
considering the hub the patterns of
human history that i've been studying
we see some things over and over and
over again as new technologies emerge
they are always first used for military
purposes for the purpose of gaining more
control more power and winning wars
waging wars it's always that way
it's only later that those technologies
uh produce spin-offs that are used in
the civilian domain
so whatever we see of ai there is a
there is a whole different ai that is
not visible to us that's being double
that's what about 20 or 30 years beyond
what we can imagine it's already that
far ahead and that is right now
being developed by various militaries in
the world
so eventually if this continues like
this it could end up
enslaving humanity or possibly
destroying humanity
eventually these ai systems even if they
are not sentient and self-aware they
could still if you give give them the
wrong kind of decision-making ability
they could say that let's optimize
everything get rid of the human
connection completely
and
you know who knows what could happen
so i am on the side of elon musk and
whichever other notable people there are
that it is a very dangerous development
for us and there needs to be
restrictions
and controls and checks and balances on
the power that ai
has and essentially the people who have
who are developing ai have
krishna sarah says have humans stopped
natural selection evolution
and will overpopulation be your end
okay so lots of people asked this
question have we stopped evolving
have humans stopped evolving
no we have not stopped evolving but we
have to understand the time scales on
which evolution is visible
human beings we our species is called
homo sapiens right
if you go back
250 000 years before today
you find skeletons ancient skeletons of
homo sapiens in in various parts of
africa typically two and a half
lakh years before today those
skeletons of homo sapiens are
anatomically and physically identical to
ours
so those are called anatomically modern
human beings
and that goes back about two and a half
lakh two and two point five lakh years
before today so in a quarter of a
million years we have not evolved
noticeably we are more or less the same
you go back a half million years you
will see significant changes you go back
a million years you will see even more
changes you go back three million years
our ancestors were the same as the
ancestors of the chimpanzees you go back
five million years ago
even the gorillas become five or six
million years before today our ancestors
and the chimpanzees and sisters and the
gorillas ancestors were the same
right
so evolution happens over very long time
scales
you don't evolve
in ten years or a hundred years or a
thousand years or a hundred thousand
years
typically
the evolution the the process of
evolution and the effects of evolution
are visible over very long time scales
lacks of years hundreds of thousands of
years
quarter of million years maybe more so
we are evolving we are certainly
evolving but we will not become a
different species
in the next hundred thousand years
unless we mess up our genetics with
various
gene editing and other
experiments right so we have not
stopped evolving evolution is still
happening but it's not visible the
effects are not visible that take that
takes a very long time to become
apparent
uh the second question is where will our
population be our end i don't think so
right now all the birth rates the
fertility rates in most of the countries
in the world are declining
in japan it's way below replacement rate
in
russia it's below replacement below the
replacement rate the replacement
fertility rate is 2.1
children per woman
that's what that's what i think it is
in india it's now two so we are below
replacement in india as well
overall overall right
uh in
all the industrialized nations in
western europe etc everywhere in turkey
in iran
you have populations that have the
entire national population that has
fallen below the replacement rate
and then
there are new
viruses etc that are emerging
uh we we are done with the previous one
now it seems there's a new one coming up
so it looks like this is the decade of
the virus and they're gonna keep on
coming up with various uh
incentives for human beings to stay
locked down and under lock and chain and
that sort of thing so i don't know so i
don't think we are going to
uh
end up
going
far beyond the current population of the
world
yeah in the very low income nations the
population is still rising in pakistan i
think the
the country is way above replacement
rate it's a very backward country it's a
very poor country it's a very
the literacy rate is very low and
typically there's a inverse correlation
between the literacy rate and the
fertility rate the higher the
literacy percentage of a nation the
lower is the rate of fertility in
pakistan it's very low and i think the
number of children per woman is about
four or more than four
but overall
if you look at the entire planet the
trend is downwards
so if this trend continues
we may even have a population crash in
the next hundred years
so let's see how that goes but i don't
it doesn't look like
overpopulation will be our end
hopefully there's no end hopefully we go
on for the next few thousand years and
uh
you know
good good future for humanity i hope so
swapnil says is it
no it is now possible to bring extinct
animals back through gene editing
techniques however could there be a case
wherein
an animal that might be brought back
from extinction might do
may do more harm to the earth than good
if yes was it worth it to have wiped out
those animals in the past by humans from
our planet in the first place okay
it is now possible so the assumption
that isn't made here the assertion
that's made here is that it's now
possible to bring extinct animals back
through gene editing techniques uh i'm
not sure it's still possible we are yet
at that stage
i can't think of a single extinct animal
that has been brought back thus far
thus far
we do have gene editing techniques the
the technology is is getting better
every few years we have something called
crispr that you can use to
edit individual genes in your insider
genome um
and we do have uh so we could and we we
do have the technique of cloning so we
have cloned various animals
uh like dollar dollar the sheep and
various other species perhaps i hope
it's not been been done to humans
because that would be weird and
unethical most likely
so yeah we have all this entire
assortment of gene editing etc
techniques
and i would say theoretically it would
be possible to bring back let's say a
mammoth
back to life
a mammoth is an extinct species of of
elephant and that species went extinct
about
10 000 years before today
so the mammoths coexisted with humans
it's it's not too long ago it's just 10
000 years it's from from an evolutionary
perspective it's yesterday
it's last evening
right
so
and we find uh preserved mammoths all
the time
in the permafrost in siberia in north
america just recently i saw on twitter
somebody discovered a baby mammoth that
was perfectly preserved in the ice
of course its dna would be available
yeah of course it would be
most likely possible
to use the various genetic techniques to
to
to bring back to give birth
to to to fertilize an egg with that sort
of
that sort of dna
yeah or take a fertilized egg
modify it's its dna profile add the the
mammoth genetics into it and then
implant that
fertilized egg into a female elephant
and that female elephant would most
likely give birth to a live
mammoth which would bring the species
back from extinction it is possible
nobody has done it thus far
for the past 20 30 years japanese
scientists had been investigating that i
am not sure how far that went
but i think it would be possible today
so if let's say we bring the mammoth
back from extinction let's let's say we
bring the dodo back from extinction
these species lived until very recently
i don't think they would do any harm to
the planet
right
so certain species if you bring them
back from extinction they would just fit
into the world properly as long as these
are species that lived until reasonably
recently the mammoth is a good example
about 10 000 years let's say you find a
way of bringing dinosaurs back to life
like in the jurassic park movies that
would be
uh that would be out of place in today's
world because the non-avian dinosaurs
were wiped out they died out about 66
million years before today in the
chicholu impact event the avian
dinosaurs survived they are all around
us
uh so let's say
you know what's happened recently i i
don't know why this news has all has
fallen off everyone's radar a few years
ago
people discovered uh
a t-rex bone a femur the thigh bone of a
t-rex
and it was entombed it was encased in
rock yeah
it's like i don't know how many million
years old or it is definitely more than
66 million years old
and for some reason the the
rock broke
and what they discovered was tissue
you know and
it was liquid tissue with with uh
what looked like the remains of
blood vessels even blood cells etc
inside the t-rex fossil thigh bone femur
yeah so if that survived all these
millions of years it it is possible that
you may be able to extract some dna out
of it
that has been hushed up it looks like
and it's i there were multiple cases of
this sort of thing happening
so it is possible
that dna could be extracted from such
uh fossils that still contain uh
intact or near intact dinosaur tissue
right
and then even if some bits of the dna
are missing you could uh
so the t the t-rex was it was
essentially a giant bird
right the tyrannosaurus rex rex it was a
massive giant bird
dinosaurs and birds are essentially the
same thing so you could use chicken dna
to fill in the gaps in the t-rex uh
genome whatever the gaps or whatever is
missing and then you could try and
recreate the species it is possible that
you may be able to
possible maybe in the next 10 20 years
you may be able to do that
you do that
will that species that you are
recreating will it fit back into the
world like the mammoths would the
mammoths lived until recently the the
world the dinosaurs lived in no longer
exists so that would possibly cause
problems
what would they eat where would they fit
into the evolutionary uh into the
environmental food chain for instance
right
because they've been missing for 66 plus
million years
so certain species if you bring them
back
would possibly
not fit into the present
ecological environmental
scenario they could possibly do more
harm than good there may be certain
genetic aspects that would that could
spread to other animals and cause
problems you know if you look at the
human genome
there's a lot of viral dna in our genome
and we don't know why it's there but
it's there
and similarly it's possible with
dinosaurs on other species also there
could be some viral components to their
dna to the genome
now
could that cause problems if you bring
it back and set it free in the
environment possibly
so one has to be very careful when you
when one is playing god you you cannot
start playing god and start bringing
extinct speeches to life without
considering it very carefully
so that's what i have to say
you bring back certain species like
recently extinct species to to life
again it should not cause too many
problems hopefully
but you bring back older species to life
it could
upset
uh the ecological balance and cause
problems
all right this is by amruta could you
please explain what exactly is the
precession of the equinoxes and why does
it need exactly 26 000 years to complete
also there are many geological evidences
that some sort of extreme calamity
happens every 26 000 years like
earthquakes floods
earthquakes floods tsunamis
is it related to the precession of the
equinoxes okay
what is the precession of the equinox
the earth is a spheroidal planet
you could approximate it to be a sphere
yeah
it's oblate it's squashed uh in a
certain way but it's nearly spherical
you could approximate it with a sphere
and it's a spinning object right so it
spins around a certain axis
the axis is not straight up with respect
to the plane of the solar system it's
tilted
right and this tilt is spinning so
a picture is worth ten thousand words
let me show you a picture an image so
that you get what i am saying instead of
me going on forever so let's bring in
the picture
of that
where is it here it is
let me enlarge this a little bit
so this is our planet the earth it is
spinning around its axis
and this axis is tilted with respect to
the ecliptic plane
right the plane of the solar system you
could you could consider it to be that
and there's a north pole and a south
pole which is
so you you can see what that is now
let's take a look at another image
so the axis of precession
itself
goes around in this manner
and the north pole right now
is pointed at this star called polaris
but 13 000 or so years ago it was
pointed at a different star called vega
right so 13 000 years ago the north pole
the polar star the pole star was vega
not polaris today it is polaris
and later it will be the star called
demeb and alpha draconis and all so this
phenomenon that you are seeing right
here right right here
is called the precession of the
equinoxes right and this entire cycle
what entire cycle
from polaris to vega and back
that
takes about 26 thousand years ago 26 000
years one
entire cycle it's actually about 25 700
or so years you can say it's about 26
000 years
so that is
called the precession of the equinoxes
hopefully that makes sense once you see
it in in that manner
the image right
so
that's just how it is in certain other
planets i'm sure it would take a
different amount of time all planets
have a certain certain amount of tilt
with respect to the plane of the solar
system and i'm not sure what the numbers
are but in other planets the planets you
would have a different amount of time
that it takes for a for entire cycle
so that's how it is so that's why
that's the amount of time it takes
uh
there are geological evidences that some
extreme calamity happens every 26 000
years i'm not sure about that you have
cycles there is something called the
bill count milkanovich cycle
that is
a climate change cycle that you can look
up
right
um
there's another cycle or or event that
happens periodically in the earth which
is the reversal of the magnetic poles
so you have north pole and south pole we
also have magnetic poles in the earth
which are more or less aligned with the
north pole and south pole that also
reverses in polarity every few i don't
know how what the what the time period
is you can look that up if you're
interested so there are multiple cycles
that are
that are there that play out again and
again and again
in our planet on our planet and you see
the events
that are a consequence of that so i am
not sure if the precession of the
equinoxes is is really related to any
earthquakes or floods or tsunamis but uh
you have a variety of various uh
climatic and other cycles that the
planet
witnesses on a regular
basis
mohawk says i want to know i want to ask
what is meant by a light year okay
that's very simple
a light year is not a unit
of time it sounds like a year right
light year it's not a unit of time it's
a unit of distance
so
light
travels at a certain speed roughly 300
000 kilometers per second
that's the speed of light
300 000
kilometers per second yeah i think
that's what it is meters kilometers
whatever it is look it up let me just
of light
speed of light what is the speed of
light
meters per second
it's 299 792 458 meters per second
so it's about 300 000 kilometers per
second
uh
yeah
three hundred thousand
three hundred thousand kilometers per
second okay so that is there is a speed
of light in one second it travels that
distance three hundred thousand or three
lakh kilometers
okay
in one second
so if you multiply that by 60
you you will come up with the amount of
distance light travels in a minute
you multiply that by 60
you will come with a bigger distance it
will give you a bigger distance that's
the amount of of of distance light
travels in an hour multiplied by that by
24 you will get the amount of distance
light travels in a day
multiply that by 365 you will get the
amount of distance light travels in one
year and that distance whatever it is
calculated is called a light year
so that is a unit of distance not time
right
so that in short is what a light year is
the amount of distance
light travels in one year that is a
light year
and the closest star in our
stellar neighborhood proxima centauri is
roughly four light years away from here
so if you shine a beam of light or torch
light in that direction it will take
slightly more than four years for that
for that light to reach that star
proxima centauri so that's what a light
year is
okay
atom heart mother
a pink floyd fly a pink floyd fan
the question is yeah pink floyd great
band
how far do you agree with the big bang
theory
is it even possible for us to predict
how the universe would have started
provided that billions of years ago all
physical laws could have been entirely
different from the present ones one
question of mine would be would be that
is there anything in the universe having
speed of more than like let's let's
concentrate on the big bang
one question per person
so
how far do i agree with the big bang
theory
it's not whether i agree or not
it makes sense
see in science in mathematics and
physics you don't believe things
there is no belief
there's no i agree with this i don't
agree with this it's not politics it's
not about opinions it's about data it's
about facts it's about it's about
evidence so let's let's talk about the
big bang theory how did
physicists come up with the big bang
theory it's not so that was some
somebody it's not like somebody dreamt
it up and everybody said okay let's
agree to this it's not about consensus
how did this happen so
in the 1920s edwin hubble
uh
came up with what's known as he what he
discovered what edwin hubble discovered
is that all galaxies
are moving
away from us
okay so he did a lot of
meticulous calculations about and how
did he find out that galaxies are
receding away from us
because these galaxies are red-shifted
when something goes further away because
of the relativistic doppler effect
the light that comes from that object
is stretched out when it's stretched out
it is shifted towards the red end of the
spectrum so there are certain elements
that give up very characteristic
wavelengths you know what they are when
you find that when you look for that you
will find that it is shifted towards the
red end of the spectrum and the more it
is shifted the further away that thing
is going away from us and the further
the speed is the velocity is so not only
are galaxies and other distant objects
going away from us they're the
the movement
is accelerating
which tells you that the universe itself
is expanding
that is why the galaxies are receding
further and further away from us and the
further you go
the faster they are moving away from us
right so uh edwin hubble came up with a
certain uh
certain value for the for what we now
call the hubble constant today we know
it's about 70 roughly 70 kilometers per
second per mega per second that is the
value
so
the first piece of the evidence
is that the universe is expanding there
is unambiguous incontrovertible evidence
from observational evidence from
observations that the universe is
expanding distant objects are moving
away from us and the more distant a
galaxy or object is the faster it is
receding from us
so the universe is expanding and the
expansion is accelerating the further
you go away
so
now
let's say you reverse the time if it is
expanding away from us in the past those
objects would have been much closer to
us
and based on the the speed of the
expansion and all those things
if you do proper detailed calculations
you will find that if you go back about
13.7 13.8 billion years before today the
entire universe would have been
compressed into a single point
right
it's clear
you just have to take the the expansion
backwards in time and you can come up
with the approximate time when the
universe was born
right so that is one thing there is no
doubt about the fact that the universe
is expanding and the expansion is
accelerating secondly
people so so it was clear that the
universe would have would have started
as a single point or something very
close to a point then
then people understood that if
everything was concentrated into a point
it would have been just pure energy
incredibly dense energy right
and then the expansion happened
which people which fred hoyle called the
big bang
so if such an event happened there would
have been an immense amount of radiation
in the past
and as the universe expanded and cooled
that primordial radiation also would
have cooled down and stretched out over
time it would also have been red shifted
over time
very clear
and if that happened
then that
radiation would still be present in the
universe today and if you know how to
detect it
at the appropriate wavelengths you
should be able to find it
so until the 1950s or so people
did not quite agree with this theory
this big bang theory they said it is
like creationism you know the christian
creation doctrine that god created the
universe and all that so they said they
said that the universe should be a
steady state universe there is no god in
all in science and you're trying to
recreate christian theology and so on
the christian theology says that the
universe was born about 4 000 years ago
in physical cosmology
the calculations were about 13
came to an answer of about 13 point
something billion years or whatever the
whatever the
initial calculations were
so most physicists at that time did not
believe in this
ridiculous idea of a big bang
fred hoyle
even even gave it the name big bang just
to make fun of it but that caught on in
the media so that's why it's called the
big bang theory it's not a bang it's not
an explosion it's an expansion
but then what happened is that this
cosmic microwave background radiation
was discovered by penzias and wilson i
think i think
so they discovered
this relic radiation the leftover
radiation that can only have come
from this big bang event
and over time we have
mapped this radiation out it's very very
uniform but over very large scales you
find
in isotropes
and
fluctuations in the levels and all that
right
so you have the planck satellite and the
wmap satellite which has given us a very
detailed map of the
background the the relic creation of the
universe
and so on so because we have the
evidence of the expansion of the
universe the accelerating expansion of
the universe and because we have
this telltale
clue of the
of the
microwave background edition the cmbr
these and and we have lots of other data
points that i will not go into because
of all these data points it is clear
that this event actually happened so
it's not about belief nobody believed it
until they found the evidence you get it
science is not about belief it's not
about agreeing with this or agreeing
with that you look at the evidence you
use the tools of science the scientific
method and if the evidence agrees with
the theory then the theory is likely to
be correct
even today the the the
the so-called big bang theory is not
perfect
it doesn't explain why this happened it
is only a chronological history of the
universe what the big bang theory the
big mac model
the lambda cdm cosmological model what
it does
is it attempts to recreate
the chronology the chronological history
of the universe it is unable to explain
why things happened why what what caused
the big bang we still don't have the
answer we are trying to figure it out
and uh there are lots of uncertainties
the very initial moments after the big
bang we don't know anything about it
more or less
yeah
the inflationary epoch the reheating
epic we have recreated much of it based
on observational evidence
so i am very clear about this all
scientists physicists cosmologists are
clear about this
the best theory that we have today about
the origin
about the history of the universe
is what we call the big bang theory
right so based on all of these things we
can actually
uncover
roughly what happened and possibly
predict what will happen in the future
right
so that's how it is
so that is my answer to uh
that question
right
the next question is the lecture
i read neil degrasse tyson's book which
says that in wherein he says that the
accelerated expansion of the universe
will
in 22 billion years in the future
end in what's called the big rip
when even atoms get ripped apart
what this will
really happen
okay so the big grip
there is there are multiple possible
scenarios about the future of the
universe one is that
the universe we know it's expanding
the expansion is accelerating by
something
which we call
dark energy we don't quite know what it
is but we we believe that we know
something called dark energy exists we
don't know what it is it seems to be
some kind of fluid some kind of
repulsive force whatever whatever it is
we don't know what it is it's there
so
one scenario is that the universe will
keep expanding the acceleration will get
the expansion will accelerate more and
more eventually
the uh
observable universe will just be our
galaxy and nothing else eventually even
that will
will fly apart and that's called the big
rip eventually even the atoms
uh atoms will be ripped apart even space
time itself will be ripped apart that's
called the big rip
another scenario is that after a certain
period of expansion the universe will
start contracting and there will be a
big crunch
and will it go and we will have the
reverse of the big bang in that in that
scenario there is something called the
big bounce model in which there will be
a big crunch then again expansion then
again a contraction it's a cyclic
process a cyclical universe
and there are various other
models as well
so whether the big rip happens or not
depends on the kind the type of dark
energy we have in our universe so uh
if the dark energy in the universe
increases without limit it would
certainly overcome all the forces that
hold the universe together the big force
that holds large scale structure
together is the force of gravitation
which is the geometry dynamics it's the
uh general relativity right it's it's
governed by what we call general
relativity so the time
to this hypothetical big rip how long
how far in the future could it happen it
depends on a number of character on a
number of parameters the first is the
equation of state parameter which is
called w or w typically which is the
ratio between the
dark energy pressure and the energy
density so if dark energy is a fluid
let's say you have a fluid a liquid in a
glass in a vessel so that this liquid
this fluid will have a certain pressure
it will have a certain density if dark
energy is a fluid of some kind it will
have a certain pressure in a certain
energy density the ratio of these two
quantities is called the equation of
state parameter which is denoted by w
the second parameter is the hubble
constant there are two possible values
of the hubble constant 67.7 kilometers
per second per mega per second or 73
kilometers per second per mega per sec
uh that's the hubble tension so that's
the hubble constant the third parameter
is the density of all the matter in the
universe
which is called omega m
so if you take the value of w to be
minus 1.5 if you take the hubble
constant to be about 70
and the density of all the matter in the
universe to be about 0.3 then i believe
you come up with a time to a future big
rip to be around 22 billion
years from the present day
if you take a different value of w for
instance
which we don't quite know yet so if you
take a bit different value it you could
get a different time for the big rip if
you take a value of w less than
a certain
certain value then you may never have a
big rip and you will have a big crunch
so it depends on what values you take
in this
calculation
so we don't quite know yet
it is possible there could be a big rip
depending on the values
and the values are something that we
don't have a lot of clarity about as of
today
so it could happen it may not happen we
don't quite know so i haven't read
the book that you're referring to he
he has a number of books very good
author obviously
very uh
very
famous and beloved astrophysicist the
people's astrophysicist so yeah it's i'm
sure that he must have come up with one
of these uh
calculations and according to one of
these scenarios you could have a big
grip in about 22 billion years
so what would a big grip look like first
all the neighboring galaxies would
disappear
they would go far away and they would be
beyond the observational range
then even our galaxy will be pulled
apart
the force of gravity will will be
defeated by the expansion of the
universe
eventually even the solar system will be
pulled apart the planets will fly off
the earth will fly off somewhere
then eventually
uh the atoms and molecules
will all dissociate
the subaromatic parts the subatomic
particles will fly off from the atoms
and in the end stage even space time
itself will be ripped apart
so that is what a big rip would look
like not a nice thing but hey
it's too far away in the future if it
ever happens
so that is about the big grip
uh ashai says how does fire cast a
shadow
yeah
fire can cast a shadow in certain
scenarios
so
what is fire
fire is what comes out from combustion
it's a lot of heat
uh in inside what is inside the flame
the the light that you see comes from
the uh
from the combustion of various particles
and in various substances
and
because it is hot it rises upwards
that's why the flame is always pointing
upwards typically unless there is wind
and inside a flame you have certain
kinds of particulate matter
soot perhaps from a candle
or the the whatever substance has been
combusted the carbon particles or
whatever it is right suit is also carbon
and it goes upwards it rises upwards
because the surrounding air is cooler
than the flame
now
not all flames cast shadows if you're in
a dark room and you light a flame it
will actually give off light it won't
cast a shadow
so in what scenarios will you have a
flame casting a shadow one scenario is
that you have a flame let's say you have
a candle a candle stick a flame on the
top
and
you shine a very bright light from
behind it towards the wall so you have a
flame here
you have a wall here and here you have a
very bright light which is brighter than
the flame itself in that case
the flame will cast a shadow
because it is obstructing the path of
this brighter light
so that is one scenario in which a flame
could cast a shadow there's another
scenario
so a flame like i said it's a very hot
substance it
warps the air
and it ends up causing
a phenomenon called optical refraction
a refraction happens when there is a
boundary between two substances
which which through which light passes a
thicker substance and a thinner
substance different temperatures or
whatever and it's it's this is the
phenomenon in which you if you put your
finger in a in a glass of water your
finger appears to be broken or bent or
or a pen or a stick or whatever
so that also happens at the interface of
a hot flame and cooler air
so it kind of warps and distorts the
path of light and that also can appear
to cast a shadow it's it's an illusion
in this case it's an illusion caused by
refraction of light
so two scenarios one in which a flame
obstructs a much brighter light and
secondly a fray a flame which causes
refraction of light which appears in the
form of a shadow so these are two
scenarios i can think of right now
okay
okay saurabh says why is there more
matter than antimatter that's uh that's
essentially an age-old mystery
so matter antimatter what is antimatter
so antimatter particles share the same
mass as your regular matter particles
their matter counterparts
but these antimatter particles have
qualities that are opposite like
electric charge is a very good example
so
we have
sub-atomic particles like the electron
like the proton etc
their antimatter counterparts
exist for the electron the electron as
you know is a negatively charged
particle its antimatter counterpart is
the positron which has the same mass but
it has a positive charge
the proton as you know is a positively
charged particle its anti-matter
counterpart is the antiproton antiproton
which is the same mass but a negative
charge
the photon of light is its own
anti-particle and so on and so forth
right
so the very early universe right after
the big bang
was pure energy just pure energy
now we know
from quantum field theory that vacuum
is not quite empty it is teeming with
particle anti-particle pairs
so from because of the heisenberg
uncertainty principle that's a whole
different story but these are virtual
particle anti-particle pairs that are
formed and they these are they they
recombine very rapidly
so
that's vacuum energy right so in the
very early universe when you had pure
energy eventually what happened is that
it gave rise to incredible
amounts of particle anti-particle pairs
with with the relation of e equal to m c
squared
and these particle anti-particle pairs
would form and disso and recombine and
give back energy again and if you if you
look at uh
see whenever we create matter in
particle accelerated
particle accelerators we typically get
and we not typically we always get an
equal amount of matter and antimatter
right but in the early universe for some
reason
even though all of these particle
anti-particle pairs should have
recombined and just given off pure
energy what happened is that in the very
early universe
approximately one particle per billion
managed to survive and there was an
excess of matter or antimatter for
whatever reason we don't know what it is
some
unknown mechanism
or law of physics or we don't know what
it is
caused this to happen a slight majority
of matter as as compared to the
anti-matter that was produced we don't
know why this happened
we don't have the answer
one of the hypothetical scenarios is
that possibly
our universe
has an anti-matter counterpart so from
the big bang not one universe came out
but two universes came out one with more
matter one with more antimatter and
today you have two parallel universes
that have come out of the big bang one
has pure one has a matter and one has
antimatter and eventually when the two
recombine in the future big crunch or
whatever it will all go back to pure
energy that is one
hypothesis it's not a theory it's a
hypothesis because it is not testable or
falsifiable
so we don't quite know
why there is more matter than antimatter
maybe some unknown
uh law of physics
exists
maybe some unknown mechanism caused this
to happen maybe we have two universes
one with matter one with antimatter we
don't know this is this this is called
barry on asymmetry
and this is something uh people uh
physicists are actively trying to
understand why it is so as of today we
don't quite have the answer
hackeristic says why why do we say that
heat can travel through vacuum
while heat is the kinetic energy of
atoms
and radiation itself is just
electromagnetic radiation
which to be generated doesn't
necessarily require heat
i don't say that heat travels through
vacuum i don't know who says that i'm
sure people say that people say all
kinds of things
what travels through vacuum
is radiation
electromagnetic radiation like you say
there's there are other forms of
radiation as well
there is actually something called
gravitational radiation gravitational
waves
uh so
so what we what happens let's take the
case of the sun
we look at the sun when the sun rises we
feel hot right we feel the heat so
people say that the sun is all these
eight light minutes away
yeah
and yet
from that far away it's giving us heat
that's what we sense that's what we feel
what really happens
is that the sun gives off
electromagnetic radiation
in the form
of photons
light waves photons wave particle
duality photons or light waves these
photons
or these light waves whatever you want
to call it they carry a certain amount
of energy
right e equals h nu in case you know
so based on the frequency of the light
there is a certain amount of energy
associated with it
this
energy this radiation travels through
vacuum it's just radiation it's just
bundles of energy
once these photons once this radiation
reaches the earth
it
interacts with the molecules
in the atmosphere
goes through that it heats up the
atmosphere
right
because molecules absorb
this energy
they vibrate
and they give off give off something
that we perceive as heat
similarly much of this radiation makes
its way through the atmosphere and it's
incident on our body on our skin on
rocks on vegetation etc and all of these
atoms and molecules absorb the energy
give it off in certain wavelengths and
also give off
infrared radiation that we perceive as
right as light so that is how the
process
roughly roughly i'm giving you a very
rough outline of what happens
yeah but that's how it is so it's not
heat that's traveling in the vacuum of
space
it is photons it is
electromagnetic radiation
that's traveling and when it reaches the
planet earth and it reaches us that's
when it interacts with the atmosphere
and all the substances on the planet and
gives off
what we call heat
okay karan says what was the purpose of
digging the cola super deep bore hole
so the cola super deep borehole
is something that was dug in the 20th
century in the ussr
a very deep
borehole a very deep hole in the surface
of the earth
i think it reached a depth of more than
12 kilometers
and it's the deepest hole that's ever
been dug anywhere in the world
right
what is the purpose to figure out what
the earth's crust is like and what
properties it has as we go further deep
inside
find out to find out what's inside what
what how it is inside curiosity
scientific curiosity
and of course it will have certain
applications so uh they found certain
interesting uh
phenomena as
they went deeper as you go deeper the
the temperature increases as you know
deep below the earth's surface and
mantle you have a magma layer which is
all molten rock so as you go deeper into
the earth's crust
as you go deeper below the earth's
surface the temperature increases it
gets hotter and hotter
so i think around
around a depth of 10 or 12 kilometers
the temperature was
i think more than 200 degrees celsius
possibly something like that look it up
if you want
so that's one thing they found they also
found lots of hydrogen in there hydrogen
gas
they also found that the rock doesn't
quite behave
from a stray from the
exactly the way it was predicted there's
a different kind of
physics
of the rock metamorphic rock or whatever
i'm not sure what it is
uh at those temperatures and pressures
the rock behaves like a plastic
at a certain depth
and that made it impossible to drill
further
so they found a number of interesting
things and it it helped us understand
the geology and the physics of the
earth's
crust the earth's crust more better yeah
so yeah so we found some interesting
data from this experiment
and eventually i think the project ran
out of funding and that's why it was
stopped
so the purpose to dig this borehole was
to understand
our planet better and that's certainly
what happened
avinash says how did life evolve from
non-living matter
and swapnil says can you please explain
the miller yuri experiment which gave
rise to the field of prebiotic chemistry
okay so these two questions are
interrelated it's about life it's called
abiogenesis
the chemical origin of life the
emergence of life possibly from
non-living
matter right
so this experiment was done in the u.s
uh in the 1950s
two guys miller and yuri i believe so
what they were doing they were testing
the possible chemical origin of life
so we know that the earth formed about
four and a half billion years before
today roughly
and it was a very different place at
that time it was a very hot
ball
of extremely hot molten rock and all
there was a lot of lot of volcanism the
composition of the atmosphere was very
different from what it is today there
was a lot of lightning and so on so
forth so they tried to recreate that
environment in
this experimental apparatus right so
what they did was um
they took a flask with methane
ch4 ammonia nh3 and hydrogen which is h2
and a different flask with water which
is h2o they come they interlink the two
and they heated the water to create
vapor steam
and they also had a spark plug in there
which would create electrical sparks all
the time to to recreate the lightning
scenario of the early earth
and they let this run for a certain
period of time and what they found is
that a number of amino acids were formed
from this procedure i don't know how
long the experiment to run
maybe
i don't know a week or so i'm not sure
look it up it ran for a certain amount
of time
and these very simple ingredients that
was that they started off with
eventually formed a number of amino
acids
amino acids so these are organic
compounds
that are the building block of life
amino acids give rise to proteins
proteins is what we have in our in our
body it's the foundation of all life on
the planet
so i think what they found at the time
was five or so amino acids but later on
many decades later when it was
reanalyzed they found well over 20
different amino acids so that's what the
experiment was i'm sure we can look it
up and let me see what the apparatus
looks like
uh
miller yuri
experiment let me
share the screen
so what did this apparatus look like
yeah so this is the experimental
apparatus that they had
there is one flask with
water methane ammonia and hydrogen in a
different
place a different flask which is
connected to this which has boiling
water on a heat source it's giving off
water vapor
and there is an uh an arrangement for
creating an electrical spark
and you run this for a certain amount of
time and then what you get is all of
these amino acids that that emerge out
of this experiment so that in brief is
the miller yuri experiment
and
yeah that is one potential
way in which life or the or the building
blocks of life could have emerged
in the very early earth
this is a biogenesis prebiotic chemistry
and so on
so that is possibly one scenario in
which life evolved from non-living
matter could this if you if you keep it
going could it give rise to dna
molecules we don't know i don't think
anybody's been able to
uh
to to
successfully
induce
the creation of dna or rna molecules in
such an experiment so that is one
mystery because all life on earth
it does come off come out of these
building blocks amino acids etc but all
life on earth whether it is the most
complex organisms like human beings and
apes and whales and all that
or whether it is the dinosaurs the
lizards
or even if you go down to the
microscopic level
bacteria viruses whatever you have all
life on earth has dna
right so where is this where did this
dna come from that's the main big real
question
so there is this uh
panspermia theory which says that dna
came from outer space
because when we when we analyze
various
uh
meteorite samples rocks that have fallen
from the sky in the form of meteorites
we often find signatures of life on
these meteorites
you know organic compounds maybe even
i'm not sure if they found amino acids
but possibly yeah
so we know that there is a lot of water
on various comets we know that there are
organic compounds in these comets and
asteroids
it is possible that something else may
also be have been there in the past who
knows
so there is one theory but there is no
evidence for this theory the the
panspans perma theory that life came
from outer space but it is a possibility
so we don't quite know as of today we
don't quite have the answers how did
life evolve from non-living matter
one possible answer is the miller urey
experiment but it doesn't answer the
question of the dna
where did dna come from where did that
emerge from
so as of today we have more questions
than answers but it's good
it means there is a lot of scope for
further research and progress
alpha beta says
do
do satellites have a specific lifetime
and on what factors
does that depend
what causes satellites to
hit the earth
they are orbiting around the earth
without any fuel getting solar energy
okay
uh why okay do satellite have do
satellites have a specific lifetime yes
it depends on a number of factors first
of all uh the components of the
satellite the the
the machinery of the satellite how long
will it last everything degrades in
vacuum in space even on earth any
machine won't last forever after a
certain time the components will wear
out
and will stop functioning so there is a
certain uh amount of time anything can
work and then it stops working
let's say you have a satellite with a
fuel source
that fuel source will have a finite
lifetime after which the electricity
will stop flowing
sometimes some satellites don't have any
fuel source energy source they have
solar panels even those solar panels
over over a few years will slowly
degrade the amount of
energy they will be able to give the
satellite will slowly decrease over time
eventually over the even that ends and
the satellite ceases to function the way
it's designed to function that is one
factor so if you have a satellite that's
let's say at a geostationary orbit 36
000 or so kilometers above the surface
of the planet then that satellite will
have a finite lifetime after which it
will not last because of these factors
which are just outlined
there is another
uh
factor that limits the lifetime of
satellites when you have satellites in
low earth orbit
let's say 200 kilometers above the
surface let's say 300 kilometers above
the surface
these satellites will
will experience something called
atmospheric drag
so technically
the atmosphere ends
at 100 kilometers above the surface of
the planet
that's technically because actually it
doesn't quite end there the atmosphere
just goes on and on for a very long way
until it becomes so diffused you can't
really differentiate the atmosphere from
outer space
but it doesn't abruptly end at 100
kilometers above the surface
so even if if a satellite is 200
kilometers above the earth's surface it
will experience collisions with
atmosphere molecules air molecules the
collisions will be very rare very
infrequent but they will be there
so this gives rise to something called
atmospheric drag which slowly over the
days weeks months years
slows down the uh the
the velocity slows down the speed
at which the satellite is orbiting the
earth and because of that
the altitude of the satellite comes down
slowly slowly slowly and the further
and the closer it comes to the surface
of the earth the higher is the
atmospheric drag
so it's a it's a self-reinforcing
phenomenon and once the satellite is low
enough
and the atmospheric drag is high enough
the satellite will break apart and burn
up in the atmosphere
so some satellites have
a rocket engine small rocket engine
which would periodically be used to
boost the orbit of the satellite but
even that rocket fuel will eventually
end
will get over right
so these are the factors
that limit the lifetime of a satellite
if it's a low earth orbit satellite it
will eventually
end up re-entering the atmospheric and
burning up hopefully not hitting the
planet so that's what happens
they just says how many years will it
take for us to mine
to mine other planets how will it change
our world as raw materials for industry
will become cheaper
so the first question
is
how long will it take for us to reach
another planet that's the first question
and we are not talking about the moon or
asteroids we're talking about other
planets
so the only other planet that is a
viable candidate for us to go to as of
today in the 21st century is mars
it's our closest neighbor
it takes between nine months to of to
slightly more than a year depending on
the time of the year to reach there if
you have a good enough rocket
and uh
so
when do we expect human beings
to reach there right now we have a few
robots
on the planet
nasa has a couple of robots at least one
robot as if i can recall
which is currently active and
operational there's a small helicopter
like drone also that's active on the
planet right now
and there are a few satellites robot
satellites in orbit including our own
mangalyaan which is still operational
so as of today we are in a position to
send robots to the planet planet with
great difficulty these robots are very
rudimentary machines they are not in a
condition
they are not capable of mining the
planet
it is expected that humans the first
human trips to mars will begin
in the 2030s most likely
and possibly it will be spacex or nasa
that will be at the forefront of that
we already have the technology for that
but it is still very risky
we could possibly send humans there or
maybe they could die on the way or maybe
we could not be able to bring them back
so we need a little more technological
progress we need to make this entire
process as
as low risk as possible because human
lives are precious so most likely in the
2030s human beings will reach mars
and if there's a big enough rocket
rocket like the spacex the biggest one
they have you could transport all kinds
of machinery there
including mining machinery
so
at the earliest within the next 20 years
you could have the first attempts
by humans to
to do some kind of mining
on mars typically it will begin with
trying to
uh
trying to chemically alter the soil in
order to produce food there or something
and possibly produce oxygen and
water from the soil from the soil of
mars
it will it will begin like that but
eventually we will start drilling deep
into the
into the crust of the
of the planet and
possibly extract minerals metals or
whatever else is of value
so the first human habitation will most
likely happen within
the next 20 years
and another 10 20 30 years and you could
have some mining activities happening on
the planet as
as the human settlement possibly grows
there right
so possibly possibly hypothetically in
the next 50 years you would have some
mining activity on mars
but what would that mining activity be
done for
it would be done in order to create a
proper sustainable habitat on that
planet
let's say you want to build a larger
mars base for permanent human settlement
you would need materials you would try
and extract those materials out of the
planet itself instead of transporting
them all the way from earth
because it takes a lot of energy to
transfer transport even one kilo of any
material from earth to mars
so the first attempts at mining would be
in order to create a more sustainable
living environment right there
not for bringing materials back to earth
so i think the first 100 or so years 200
years possibly
whatever mining happens on mars would be
for for creating an expanding
uh human settlement not for bringing
anything back to earth
eventually
possibly
perhaps
you may have some materials which are
valuable
on earth which could be transported from
mars to earth maybe from some asteroids
to earth possibly
but there will be a very high cost for
the transportation to happen
so i am not sure if it will really
change our world
and transform our raw materials in
industry eventually if things go well
you could have permanent human
settlements on mars
and industries which possibly target
certain asteroids
so that's that sort of thing could
happen in the next two three hundred
years
so that's how i envisage this as going
initially the human settlement on mars
will be a very small scale thing it will
be tough for them to survive and they
will try to expand that settlement and
make it more future proof
so that's how i see it going
human settlements will happen over the
next
30 to 100 years and the mining will
proceed from beyond that at any
sustainable level that's how i see it
let's see
okay flying raven says some time ago i
heard about a discovery of a white hole
what's a white hole what are the
properties of a white hole a white hole
is just like a black hole but it's like
a time reversed black hole
so in the in a black hole you have an
event horizon
and whatever crosses the event horizon
is gone forever essentially
from a classical general relativity
perspective
so in a black hole everything goes
inwards typically
in a white hole it's like you have the
time reversal of a black hole
everything comes out of a white white
hole nothing can ever go in a white hole
also has an event horizon
and that is the point at which nothing
can cross into the white hole
so
a white hole would have similar
gravitational properties like a black
hole
but from time to time it would throw out
material
from within itself
and possibly it could get smaller
possibly right
so
there are certain solutions of the
einstein equations that give
you white hole solutions you know white
holes
so that's what a white hole is we have
never ever discovered i'm not sure
whether you heard about the discovery of
a white hole but yeah
we don't know
if we have ever discovered one if there
is a white hole somewhere it it would
look from far away just like a black
hole
there are certain black holes that are
very massive super massive black holes
most galaxies have a supermassive black
hole at their center
some of these are active galactic nuclei
which give off these massive giant
jets of radiation and material
right because of the accretion disk that
is around the black hole so maybe this
could be white holes that are giving off
these jets and material coming out of
that so we can't quite tell from far
away whether what we are seeing is a
white hole or a black hole from up from
afar it looks more or less the same
if it's an isolated white hole we could
be able to tell perhaps that it's a
white hole and not a black hole but we
are so far away and these objects are
typically found at the center of
galaxies which are enormous distances
away from here
millions of light years from here so we
can't quite tell but from the
theoretical perspective from the
perspective of general relativity white
holes should exist could exist
but we have never discovered one but to
to make it very simple a white holy is
like a time reversed black hole in a
black hole everything goes inside in a
white hole everything goes outside
both have an event horizon which is the
boundary of no return
so that is what a white hole is in very
very brief
okay sauraj says why is israel not
making reusable rockets why do we have
such tiny rockets with very little
payload capacity
when will isro come out of its space
taxi program it's a is it a money
problem or something else
can we wait till the time india reaches
10 trillion dollars of its gdp
uh
don't you think we'll be left if we wait
we'll be left behind in the space race i
think we need to start taking israel
forward for the longest time we have a
couple of rockets the gslv and the pslv
the pslv is the workhorse which is
actually a rocket with a very small
payload capacity it only reaches polar
orbits
the the gslv is designed to reach
geostationary orbits 36 000 or so
kilometers above the surface but even
that is not a very powerful rocket it's
the most powerful one we have
it's not
very powerful when we compare it with
other space programs and other rockets
that other countries have
so why are we not taking it forward our
rocket engineers we call the rocket
scientists are very much capable
of building more powerful rockets
very easy we have the technology to do
that we have the know-how for doing that
it's all about the funding the finances
you get a higher budget and if you get
the go ahead from the whoever
is in the decision-making
capability then this will happen
it can happen very rapidly
we could have a way more powerful rocket
in the next five or ten years if we give
the go ahead and we give the right
amount of money
and why are we not making reusable
rockets i don't understand why
spacex has been doing it for like close
to a decade now if not more
if a private company can do it why can't
israel do it with the government support
and all that
so it's all about uh political will i
would say so i'm not sure why it's not
happening i would like to see isro
go ahead
of its competitors we have the money
why don't we fund israel and give the
scientists the go ahead to explore
everything
that everybody else is doing and go
ahead of the of the competitors we have
the ability
we have the ability to go ahead of china
of japan
even spacex in the next 10 20 years if
the funding is made available and if the
scientists are given the right
directions and the permission to go
ahead
so i don't know why it's not happening i
would like to see it happen i've been
saying this for a very long time
if we wait for 20 years we'll be we'll
we will be left
a long way behind
our competitors so i hope
something is done about this
naman says what is relativistic speed
when two particles of a certain mass are
moving at let's say
99.99 the speed of light
and t parallel to each other which means
in this direction coming towards each
other
the relative speed shall be more than
the speed of light are you sure
so the question is how does relativistic
speed justify einstein's special theory
of relativity
you need to study
einstein's special theory of
relativity uh
lorenz transformations relativistic
velocity addition all that and you will
see it's not the case
even if two particles are moving at the
speed of light
if two photons are moving towards each
other at the speed of light so this guy
is at the speed of light this guy is the
speed of light and if i'm sitting here
i will see
the other guy coming to me not at twice
the speed of light but only at the speed
of light that's how velocity addition
happens
in
special relativity so let me show you
how this works i
let me demonstrate what it is let me
share my screen
one second give me a second
and i will actually try and demonstrate
this so to understand this you i cannot
explain to you in a explain this to you
in um
in a way that makes sense intuitively
relativity doesn't make intuitive sense
quantum mechanics doesn't make sense
from an intuitive perspective so let's
talk about the velocity addition
so this is the formula
that governs
velocity addition we are applying the
lorentz transformations to the
velocities right
so you have something that's coming in
one direction at 0.8 times the speed of
light
and the other one is coming at 0.9 times
the speed of light and then yet when you
add it up it doesn't add up to 1.6 times
the speed of light
so let's go to basic application
okay
so relativistic relative velocity there
is va and vb in two different directions
let's say you are saying that va is 0.99
times the speed of light i am entering
that
and vb in the opposite direction is
minus 0.99 times the speed of light
then what you get is
0.99999494 whatever
c it doesn't add up
to
or 1.8 or whatever times the speed of
light it does not it adds up to less
than the speed of light even though both
are almost the speed of light so that's
how it works you have to study the
equations you will study the theory and
then you will realize it's not quite the
case
so uh you can look it up the the
mathematics is quite simple actually
compared to the general relativity
mathematics
so that's how it works
so to understand how these things work
you have to actually study the physics
study the math
i can tell you but you won't believe it
most likely because it doesn't make
sense to you so unless you go deep into
the physics and you actually study the
equations and how they are constructed
how they are derived only then
will you understand
but that's how it works
the cosmic speed limit is the speed of
light nothing can travel
further faster than the speed of light
and if you have if a particle has mass
it cannot even reach the speed of light
it will always be below the speed of
light and there are all these
relativistic effects like uh
time dilation and so on and so forth
when it comes to these phenomena
okay
okay let's take one more question
marcus says is a plant-based or vegan
diet healthier than a diet that includes
animal products
does dairy and meat
uh cause cancer
there are many controversial
controversial opinions among scientists
floating online
are there is there any reliable
scientific evidence from either side
what's your take on this
um there seems to be very clear a
correlation between processed red meat
between red meat high consumption of red
meat and cancer
the problem with these studies is that
most of these studies if not
all of them
are sponsored by various corporations
in the 1960s in the u.s
doctors used to say that uh
doctors used to advertise their favorite
brand of of of tobacco of cigarette
camel and and so on you can see that see
the ads online even today you can see
that on google if you do a google search
so doctors
and the medical industry
have for the longest time in the west in
the us
being
co-opted and paid
to push out propaganda
and today even today you have the meat
industry hiring doctors
and
paying them to come up with various
studies which are published in medical
journals
scientific journals we don't quite know
how accurate these studies are and how
true they are it's always possible to
fudge the data to cherry pick certain
cases and ignore certain cases
so we don't know
there are so many opinions among
scientists
but what seems to be the case from my
perspective is that
the more vegetables you eat the
healthier you are and the less meat you
eat the healthier of course you need
protein
you can
you can consume more dairy or more
legumes
to get your protein you can get your
full protein profile that you need for a
day
from a completely plant-based diet that
has been more or less prone now
all right
the the meat industry disagrees with
that they will they will have scientists
who will say that you will not get your
complete protein profile your full
protein profile only from eating legumes
and vegetable and plant products you
need some meat or dairy
typically meat they'll push meat that's
not quite the case
so from my perspective from everything
i've read and studied over the decades
my perspective is that if you minimize
your intake of red meat
or meat
and if you maximize the amount of plant
based food you eat you're going to be
healthy
the more plants you eat the more
plant-based food you eat the healthier
you are and that's something i think
most studies do bear up with you know
they do show that
so my opinion it's again an opinion i i
have not done actual research in this
i've only read lots of research about
this so from all i've read this is what
i feel this is what i this is what i
have concluded you need to eat lots of
plant-based food
if you are a meat eater try and eat more
white meat
and minimize the amount of red meat that
you eat
and dairy would be actually better
because dairy can give you all the
protein you need
uh dairy doesn't seem to cause cancer
red meat seems to cause cancer
right
so that's how
that that's what makes sense to me from
my perspective right
right
okay let me take about five minutes of
questions
from the uh
from the light live chat in case you
have questions for me that you would
like to ask me right now in the live
chat this is the time i'll take a few
questions
let's uh
um
okay this is by samhita
uh what is actually about the planet
nine that has recently been discovered
we have not discovered planet nine yet
pluto used to be planet nine nine
now they have reclassified it as a minor
planet or whatever else they call it i
don't know what they call it nowadays i
don't care for me i grew up considering
pluto as planet 9 and that's what i call
it
now
uh there is news
about the possible existence of an
unknown planet out
out in the far reaches of the solar
system it is possible it may even be
likely how do we come up with these
these scenarios
it's because we can infer
the presence of a massive object at a
certain distance from the sun based on
the kind of orbital
effect it would have on smaller planets
minor planets etc so there are multiple
objects in the solar system that have
been discovered that have very strange
orbits and that can only be caused
or most likely be caused by the presence
of an unknown massive and large object
at a certain distance from the sun so
the this pattern that astronomers have
observed they have discovered lots of
planets over the past 20 years that
exhibit this strange orbital
uh
path
so it looks like there is something out
there that is that has caused these
minor planets another
caper belt objects
to acquire this weird
tilted etc of orbits so there seems to
be something out there
a massive
planet which is currently very dark
which is not visible
maybe a planet that is multiple times
the size of the earth from the mass
perspective so there could be something
out there and that's what the search is
on for
some people say there could even be a
black hole orbiting the sun that we are
not aware of you know if if it's a black
hole it's dark and if it's so far away
it's not going to
do any mischief you know like the kind
of mischief black holes cause in science
fiction no a black hole out there in
orbit around the sun
could do maybe it's a primordial class
black hole you know smaller than the sun
so it doesn't have massive massive
gravitational effects and it's still
sitting out there
so that is also a possibility so maybe
our planet nine could be a hidden black
hole in our
stellar backyard
so it's not been discovered everyone is
searching for it there is a certain
amount of likelihood that it may exist
and let's see what time tells us
it would be interesting it would be
fascinating to discover a large planet
hidden somewhere far away from the sun
but it's orbiting the sun that would be
fascinating
so let's see
okay
any other questions
recommend your favorite favorite near
accurate sci-fi movies or the last one i
saw which was good was interstellar that
was near accurate
uh the way that black hole the
supermassive black hole was depicted
made sense from physics perspective the
time dilation that is that is
experienced by the by the hero
also made sense from a physics
perspective the last part of the movie
in which he goes into a black hole and
encounters a tesseract or whatever that
was all hypothetical but apart from it
overall it was a very good movie
uh so that's one movie that i that i
liked a lot
there's another movie called arrival
which is nonsense
some people say arrival is so good
i found it ridiculous
uh yeah so
favorite near accurate sci-fi movies one
is
like i said interstellar there's another
one called solaris there is one called
um
what is it called it's based off a novel
by arthur c clarke 2001 a space odyssey
which is about
a sentient computer
hal 2000 i believe it was called
there's lots um there's lots maybe i'll
make a video about movie recommendations
how about that
okay let's see something else
maybe one or two more questions
somebody's asking questions about
history today is the day of science
um
okay i think
how do scientists say that the universe
is expanding
because of observational evidence you
look at a galaxy
and so first of all we have to
decide how far a galaxy is from us
let's say you discover a galaxy and you
don't know how far it is so you take
advantage of certain things like
standard candles type one a supernova in
which we can actually determine the
distance from us between us and them
between us and that place so there are
certain ways of discovering how far a
galaxy is so then so first we establish
the distance secondly we look at the
spectra
you know the light spectra that come
from the galaxy and there are certain
spectral lines that we know what are the
wavelengths we look for those spectral
lines in a spectrograph spectrometer
whatever and then we will find
invariably
in all galaxies apart from the andromeda
galaxy we will find that these spectral
lines are shifted towards the red end of
the spectrum it's called gravitational
it's called redshift
redshift happens when the light source
is moving far moving away from you it's
the relativistic doppler effect
so you find that all galaxies are red
shifted
and the further a galaxy away is away
from us the more red shifted it is which
tells you that not only is the universe
expanding
but the expansion is accelerating so we
have determined that the universe is
expanding based on observational
evidence
hope that makes sense
should i take one more question
how to do independent research in
mathematics or in theoretical physics
you have to become really proficient
in the subject
if you can do that then you can do
actual research the first thing in
learning physics is to become really
really really proficient in math
the mathematical methods that underlie
physics all your basic math you know
calculus differential equations integral
calculus differential calculus linear
algebra matrices blah blah blah all that
stuff pick up any textbook of
um the mathematical methods of physics
meribos is one uh and so on
i may have a few here
and you need to get get really
proficient at that you need to spend
hundreds of hours solving math problems
there's no shortcut to it
minimum time period five years
dedicated
hard work you do that you'll become
really good at math if you are really
good at math physics is the easiest
thing in the world
physics is all math
physics makes a lot of sense all
entire sense once you get the math down
you do that you can do research of
course you will have to study the
various theories quantum quantum
mechanics even though you may know the
math
is a big shock to you you know the first
time you encounter it
and especially when you start
going deeper into it so you need to get
into quantum physics quantum mechanics
quantum field theory
quantum electrodynamics chromodynamics
you need to also study relativity if
that's what you're into
so it takes a lot of time
to get there but once you are
professional enough you can do your own
research you don't need to be part of a
university or whatever else so that is
the the brief
guide
or map which is not brief and it
certainly is not easy
that's how we do it
all right gentlemen all right ladies all
right friends all right my dear
earthlings i am done for today thank you
very much for all the wonderful
questions i'm getting lots more but i'm
gonna have to stop it here for today
we'll do it again next week we will
continue this science episodes as well
this is what interests me the most this
is my core competence
and i really enjoy talking about science
so we will do this next week again and
we'll keep on doing it thank you very
much
and i will see you in the next episode